Harry W. Frantz Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Harry W. Frantz Papers 1919-1965 (bulk 1929-1937)
MSS84190
Frantz, Harry W. (Harry Warner), 1891-1982
350 items
8 containers plus 17 oversize
3.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Journalist. Scrapbooks and printed matter related to aviation, a field Franz covered for United Press International.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Curtis, Arthur E.--Correspondence.; Frantz, Harry W. (Harry Warner), 1891-1982.; Howard, Roy Wilson, 1883-1964--Correspondence.; Manduley, Manuel DeJ.--Correspondence.; McCandlish, B. V. (Benjamin Vaughan), 1886-1975--Correspondence.; Van Dusen, William, 1901-1976.
Organizations
Pan American Airways Corporation.; United Press International.
Subjects
Aeronautics, Commercial.; Aeronautics--Flights.; Aeronautics--History.; Airlines--Public relations.; Airlines.; Endurance flights.; Journalism, Aeronautical.
Occupations
Journalists.
Provenance
The papers of Harry W. Frantz, journalist, were transferred to the Library of Congress from the Historian's Office of the United States Coast Guard in 1998.
Transfers
Maps have been transferred to the Georgraphy and Map Division where they are identified as part of the Harry W. Frantz Papers.
Related Material
A collection of papers focusing on Frantz's career as a political reporter can be found at the Harry S. Truman Library, Independence, Missouri.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Harry W. Frantz are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1891, Nov. 5 Born, Cerro Gordo, Ill.
1913 1919 Attended Stanford University, Stanford, Calif.
1917 1965 Correspondent, United Press International
1924 Married Kathleen Hargrave
1936 Passenger correspondent, Pan American Airways inaugural transpacific China Clipper press flight, Alameda, Calif., to Manilla, Philippines
1939 Passenger correspondent, Pan American Airways inaugural transatlantic Yankee Clipper press flight, New York, N.Y., to Marseilles, France
1941 1944 Press director, Office of Inter-American Affairs, State Department
1944 1945 Information officer, assistant secretary of state for American republics
1982, Apr. Died, Ithaca, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Harry W. Frantz (1891-1982) span the years 1919-1965, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1929-1937. The collection is focused entirely on aviation, a field Frantz covered as a correspondent for United Press International, and documents pioneering long distance and endurance flights and the early history of the Pan American Airways Corporation and other commercial passenger and freight air carriers.
The Frantz Papers comprise three series, Scrapbooks, Printed Matter, and Oversize. The Scrapbooks are organized in a numerical system of Frantz's devising. Loose leaf scrapbooks have been dismantled and the contents foldered in the original page order. Hard bound scrapbooks are in Oversize. The monographs, pamphlets, reports, serials, publicity material, and other print and near print material that comprise the Printed Matter are arranged chronologically under United States, other countries, and Pan American Airways Corporation headings.
Volumes 19-21 of the Scrapbooks consist of Pan American Airways publicity director William Van Dusen's "Dear Señor" letters, an informal newsletter, 1937-1940, disseminating inside information on such topics as routes, personnel, technological progress, and the latest developments in the Clipper and Stratoliner programs. Other correspondents include Arthur E. Curtis, Roy Wilson Howard, Manuel DeJ. Manduley, and B.V. McCandlish.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in three series:
Scrapbooks, 1923-1954
Printed Matter, 1919-1965
Oversize, 1923-1954
Container List
- Scrapbooks, 1923-1954 (Box 1-4)
  Scrapbooks containing correspondence, book jackets, newspaper clippings, magazine articles, pamphlets, photographs, and miscellaneous printed matter.
  Arranged in a numerical order established by Frantz.
  - Vol. 1, re books by and about aviators, 1928-1931, undated See Oversize (Box 1)
  - Vol. 2, pioneering flights, biographical material re pilots, and summaries of aviation progress, 1927-1954, undated (Box 1)
  - Vol. 3, United States Army around-the-world flight of 1924, 1924-1931 (Box 1)
  - Vol. 4, articles by Frantz and others, correspondence, and memorabilia, 1937-1954, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Vol. 5, aviation before the Charles A. Lindbergh transatlantic flight, clippings, articles, maps, charts, and printed matter, 1923-1929, undated 1923-1929, undated See Oversize (Box 1)
  - Vol. 6, Latin American aviation, 1926-1948, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Vol. 7, United States civil aviation, 1929-1944, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Vol. 8, pioneering flights, 1927-1928 See Oversize (Box 2)
  - Vol. 9, pioneering flights, 1927-1928 See Oversize (Box 2)
  - Vol. 10, pioneering flights, 1927-1928 See Oversize (Box 2)
  - Vol. 11, Richard E. Byrd, Antarctic expedition and flight over South Pole, 1928-1929 See Oversize (Box 2)
  - Vol. 12, Richard E. Byrd and others, Antarctic flights and exploration, 1929-1930 See Oversize (Box 2)
  - Vol. 13, pioneering flights, 1929, 1939 See Oversize (Box 2)
  - Vol. 14, pioneering flights, 1929, 1939 See Oversize (Box 2)
  - Vol. 15, Pan American Airways Corp., pioneering transpacific Clipper flights, 1936-1945, undated (Box 2)
  - Vol. 16, pioneering transatlantic passenger flights, 1937-1941, undated (Box 2)
  - Vol. 17, pioneering transpacific flights, 1936-1939, undated (Box 2)
  - Vol. 18, Pan American Airways Corp., miscellaneous material, 1930-1940, undated (Box 2)
  - Vols. 19-21, Pan American Airways Corp., William Van Dusen, (director of public relations), background correspondence, 1937-1940, (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - Vol. 22, bibliographic and scientific material, 1929-1938, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Vol. 23, Richard E. Byrd and others, pioneering flights, 1927, undated See Oversize (Box 3)
  - Vol. 24, miscellaneous flights, 1929-1930, undated See Oversize (Box 3)
  - Vol. 25, miscellaneous flights, 1929-1930, undated See Oversize (Box 3)
  - Vol. 26, miscellaneous flights, 1929-1930, undated See Oversize (Box 3)
  - Vol. 27, re books by and about aviators, 1928-1931, undated See Oversize (Box 3)
  - Vol. 28, re books by and about aviators, 1928-1931, undated See Oversize (Box 3)
  - Vol. 29, re books by and about aviators, 1928-1931, undated See Oversize (Box 3)
  - Vol. 30, miscellaneous flights, 1929-1930, undated See Oversize (Box 3)
  - Vol. 31, Wiley Post and Harold Gatty, around the world flight, 1930 (Box 4)
- Printed Matter, 1919-1965 (Box 4-8)
  Monographs, pamphlets, reports, schedules, magazines, and other material.
  Arranged by subject and thereunder chronologically.
  - Aviation literature (Box 4)
    - United States (Box 4)
      - 1921-1937, (6 folders) (Box 4)
      - 1938-1965, (5 folders) (Box 5)
      - Undated, (1 folder) (Box 5, Box 6)
    - Other countries (Box 6)
      - 1919-1939, (5 folders) (Box 6)
      - Undated (Box 6)
  - Pan American Airways Corp. (Box 7)
    - Miscellany, 1936-1939, undated, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - New Horizons, 1940-1943, undated (Box 7)
    - Pan American Air Ways (Box 7)
      - 1936-1937, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - 1936-1937, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - 1938-1939, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Trippe, Juan T., 1937-1941 (Box 8)
- Oversize, 1923-1954 (Box OV 1-OV 17)
  Scrapbooks
  Organized and described according to the series from which they were removed.
  - Scrapbooks (Box OV 1)
    - Vol. 1, 1927-1954, undated (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
    - Vol. 5, 1923-1929, undated (Container 1) (Box OV 2)
    - Vol. 8, 1927-1928 (Container 2) (Box OV 3)
    - Vol. 9, 1927-1928 (Container 2) (Box OV 4)
    - Vol. 10, 1927-1928 (Container 2) (Box OV 5)
    - Vol. 11, 1928-1929 (Container 2) (Box OV 6)
    - Vol. 12, 1929-1930 (Container 2) (Box OV 7)
    - Vol. 13, 1929 (Container 2) (Box OV 8)
    - Vol. 14, 1939 (Container 2) (Box OV 9)
    - Vol. 23, 1927, undated (Container 3) (Box OV 10)
    - Vol. 24, 1929-1930, undated (Container 3) (Box OV 11)
    - Vol. 25, 1929, undated (Container 3) (Box OV 12)
    - Vol. 26, 1930, undated (Container 3) (Box OV 13)
    - Vol. 27, 1929, undated (Container 3) (Box OV 14)
    - Vol. 28, 1930, undated (Container 3) (Box OV 15)
    - Vol. 29, 1930-1931, undated (Container 3) (Box OV 16)
    - Vol. 30, 1929-1930 (Container 3) (Box OV 17)